American Philosophical Society. Historical and Literary Committee. American Indian Vocabulary Collection 1784-1828 Mss.497.V85
American Philosophical Society
American Philosophical Society Historical and Literary Committee, American Indian Vocabulary Collection
1784-1828
Mss.497.V85
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet
Beginning in the 1790s, the American Philosophical Society began to accumulate vocabularies and texts written in Native American languages, guided by Thomas Jefferson's idea of using comparative linguistics to reconstruct the histories of Indian peoples and discern their origins. The American Indian Vocabularies Collection was initially assembled by the Historical and Literary Committee of the APS for publication in 1816. They include information on seventeen North American languages and one each from the Caribbean and Central America, collected between 1784 and 1828. A number of individuals were invovled in recording the vocabularies, including Benjamin Hawkins, William Thornton, David Campbell, Daniel Smith, Constantine Volney, Constantine Rafinesque, William Vans Murray, John Heckewelder, Martin Duralde, Campanius Holm, and Jefferson himself. Most followed the standardized word set established by Jefferson.
American Philosophical Society. Historical & Literary Committee.
Bibliography
Peter S. Du Ponceau, "Report of the Corresponding Secretary...," Transactions of the Historical and Literary Committee of the American Philosophical Society 1 (1819): xvii-1.
Early American History Note
These three volumes contain APS's correspondence and records relating to Native American languages. MOLE contains a detailed inventory of the collection. The first volume contains extensive correspondence on Native American languages, some of which is addressed to Thomas Jefferson. Much of this material is from the early to mid nineteenth centutry. The second volume contains Thomas Jefferson's printed form that he sent out to individuals asking for Native American language information. The third volume contains photostats of a dictionary of the Miami language.
Other Finding Aids note
The vocabularies are also described in the online Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society.
Related Archival Materials note
Among several other Indian language collections at the APS, two are directly related to the Historical and Literary Committee Collection:
Thomas Jefferson's comparative vocabulary ( Call no. 497.3 J35), which includes
Du Ponceau's Indian Vocabulary Collection ( Call no. 497.3 In2) includes information on 73 languages. The North American languages recorded by Du Ponceau provided the basis for Albert Gallatin's "A Synopsis of the Indian Tribes Within the United States East of the Rocky Mountains and in the British and Russian Possessions in North America," Transactions and Collections of the American Antiquarian Society 2 (1836): 1-422.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired by the Historical and Literary Committee of the APS from John G. E. Heckewelder, Peter Stephen Du Ponceau, Thomas Jefferson and others, 1816-1828.
Scope and Contents note
The vocabularies comprising the American Indian Vocabulary Collection were assembled by the Historical and Literary Committee in 1816, when preparing for the first volume of their Transactions. The resulting collection consists of 23 vocabularies of 19 languages collected between 1784 to 1828, along with letters of transmittal and other associated information. A number of individuals were invovled in recording the vocabularies, including Benjamin Hawkins, William Thornton, David Campbell, Daniel Smith, Constantine Volney, Constantine Rafinesque, William Vans Murray, John Heckewelder, Martin Duralde, Campanius Holm, and Jefferson himself.
The majority of the vocabularies record languages in what is now the eastern half of the United States, ranging from Osage, Quapaw, and Shawnee in the lower Mississippi Valley to Natick and Mohegan in New England. Rafinesque submitted vocabularies for two non-North American languages, the extinct Taino language of Haiti and for Chontal in Central America, and Jefferson himself recorded one vocabulary, Unquachog from the Pusspatock settlement near Brookhaven, Long Island.
A number of the original printed forms of the Jefferson vocabulary (ca. 1790-1792) are included. These materials were in many instances copied by Peter S. Du Ponceau into his private collection of Indian vocabularies (Mss. 497 In2) and were, in this form, utilized by Albert Gallatin for his Synopsis (1836). Gallatin had also seen the Jefferson manuscripts.
Biographical/Historical note
The indigenous languages of the Americas first became a significant interest at the American Philosophical Society under the Society's third President, Thomas Jefferson. In his Notes on the State of Virginia (1783), Jefferson had laid the conceptual foundation for reconstructing a history of Indian peoples based upon a systematic analysis of their languages, and while he collected some vocabularies himself to that end, he was remarkably effective at spurring others. Most famously, in about 1791 he had a form printed that included a standard vocabulary of about 280 English words with adjacent blanks in which Indian equivalents were to be recorded. Distributed to his friends, military officers, and others likely to come into contact with Indians, the forms were returned to Jefferson for analysis, and over the course of decade, he accumulated over 400 vocabularies. Unfortuantely, many of these were destroyed in 1809, with the remainder arriving at the APS in 1817.
Since Jefferson's initial efforts, several other APS members have contributed to the project. The Historical and Literary Committee took a special interest in Indian vocabularies, as they did in other historical documents, publishing an important collection of them as the first volume of their Transactions in 1816. The head of the committee, Peter Stephen Du Ponceau, prefaced this volume with the statement that he was not wedded to any particular theory of Indian origins, but wished only to obtain a "bird's eye view" of them all to guage the depth of linguistic diversity in North America and to discern how these languages relate to those of the Old World. The APS has collected materials on Indian languages continuously since that time.
Barbour, James, 1775-1842; Barton, Benjamin Smith, 1766-1815; Bromley, Walter; Butrick, Daniel S.; Campanius Holm, Johan, 1601-1683; Campbell, David; Du Ponceau, Peter Stephen, 1760-1844; Duralde, Martin; Gambold, John; Gurley, George; Hawkins, Benjamin, 1754-1816; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823; Izard, George; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Kells, Richard; Little Turtle, 1747-1812; Murray, William Vans, 1760-1803; Rafinesque, C. S., (Constantine Samuel ), 1783-1840; Senseman, Gottlob, 1745-1800; Smith, Daniel, 1748-1818; Thornton, William, 1759-1828; Volney, C.-F., (Constantin François), 1757-1820; Wells, William; Zeisberger, John, 1721-1808; Atacapas language; Cherokee language; Chickasaw language; Chippewa language; Choctaw language; Chontal language; Creek language; Delaware language; Indians of North America--Languages; Language and Linguistics; Language Material; Lexica; Linguistics; Massachusett language; Miami language (Ind. and Okla.); Micmac language; Mohegan language; Munsee language; Nanticoke language; Native America; Native American Materials; Osage language; Quapaw language; Quinnipiac language; Taino language; Unquachog language
- Vocabularies and Correspondence, 1784-1828; 0.25 lin. feet
  - List of vocabularies communicated by Jefferson, Heckewelder, and Murray, 1; 1p.; [Peter S. DuPonceau]
  - ALS to John Vaughan, Oct. 5, 1820; 1a; 1p.; Peter S. DuPonceau
    Scope and Contents note
    List of additional vocabularies communicated
  - Address sheet to Thomas Jefferson, ca.1809; 1b; 1p.
    Note: "papers which were lost in the trunk no. 28 found on the S. side of the river 3 or 4 miles above Manchester & returned to me by Mr. Jefferson July 2, 1809."
  - Endorsement, Oct 1825; 1c; 1p.; [John Vaughan]
    In hand of John Vaughan: "Indian vocabularies sent to A.P. Soc. By Thos. Jefferson."
  - Vocabulary of the Cherokee and Choctaw languages, prior to 1784; 2; 8p.; Hawkins, Benjamin, 1754-1816
    Communicated by Jefferson, with note in his hand attributing authorship to Benjamin Hawkins
    Freeman and Smith 663
  - Vocabulary of the Miami language taken in part from Little Turtle, Jan. 11, 1802; 3; 17p.; W[illiam] Thornton
    Communicated by Jefferson, with note attirbuting to William Thornton, as taken from Little Turtle and William Wells, the translator
    Freeman and Smith 2225
  - ALS to Thomas Jefferson, July 12, 1800; 4; 4p.; Hawkins, Benjamin, 1754-1816
    Letter of transmittal accompanying vocabulary no. 5, and describing informants and conditions of collection
    Freeman and Smith 809
  - A comparative vocabulary of the Muskoges, or Creek, Chickasaw, Chocktaw, and Cherokee languages, [1800]; 5; 15p.; Hawkins, Benjamin, 1754-1816
    Freeman and Smith 662 and 810
  - Vocabulary of the Cherokee language, [received August 5, 1800]; 6; 8p.; [David Campbell]
    Freeman and Smith 649
  - ALS to [Thomas Jefferson], July 6, 1800; 7; 1p.; Daniel Smith
    Letter of transmittal accompanying vocabulary no. 8
    Freeman and Smith 702
  - Vocabulary of the Chickasaw Indians, Tennessee, July 6, 1800; 8; 2p.; [Daniel Smith]
    Freeman and Smith 703
  - Vocabulary of the Miami Indians, March, 1798; 9; 4p.; Chasseboeuf, Constantin François, comte de Volney
    Employing Jefferson's printed form for vocabulary
    Freeman and Smith 2226
  - Suite du vocabulaire de la langue des Atacapas, April 13, 1802; 10; 8p.; Martin Duralde
    Freeman and Smith 422
  - Vocabulaire de la langue des Chatimachas et Croyance des Chetimachas, April 23, 1802; 11; 9p.; Martin Duralde
    Includes commentary on Chitimacha religion
    Freeman and Smith 729
  - ALS to William Dunbar, April 24, 1802; 12; 11p.; Martin Duralde
    Letter of transmittal accompanying vocabularies no. 10, 11, in French, with commentary on the Indians and collection of information.
    Freeman and Smith 421
  - Translation of ALS to William Dunbar, April 24, 1802; 13; 7p.; Martin Duralde
  - Vocabulary of the Unquachog Indians, 1791; 14; 2p.; [Thomas Jefferson]
    Freeman and Smith 2335
  - ALS to [Thomas] Jefferson, Sept. 18, 1792; 15; 2p.; William Vans Murray
    Letter of transmittal accompanying vocabulary no. 16, with brief comments on the Nanticokes.
    Freeman and Smith 2365
  - Vocabulary of the Nanticoke Indians, Sept. 18, 1792; 16; 1p.; [William Vans Murray]
    Submitted on Jefferson's printed vocabulary form.
    Freeman and Smith 2366
  - Vocabulary of the Delaware Indians, Dec. 1792; 17; 1p.
    Freeman and Smith 1190
  - Vocabulary [broadside], ca.1792; 18; 1p.; [Thomas Jefferson]
    Blank version of Jefferson's printed vocabulary form.
    Freeman and Smith 2051
  - Mahicanni [Mohegan] words taken down from the mouth of one of that nation who had been born in Connecticut, 19; 8p.; J[ohn G. E.] H[eckewelder]
    Freeman and Smith 2077
  - Vocabulary of the Shawanese [i.e. Miami] language, 20; J[ohn G. E.] H[eckewelder]
    "Taken down by means of a White Woman who had been 20 Years a Prisoner with that Nation." Despite the identification, the language is Miami, not Shawnee.
    Freeman and Smith 3670
  - Comparative vocabulary of the Delaware, Minsi, Mohicon, Natick, Chippeway, Shawanoe [i.e. Miami], and Nanticoke languages, 21, 22b; 6p.; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    See also Heckewelder to Du Ponceau, July 14, 1828.
    Freeman and Smith 349
  - Comparative vocabulary of the Lenni Lenape, Mahicanni, Nanticoke, Shawano, Natick, Chippuwa and Algonquin languages, 22, 22a; 3p.; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823
    Freeman and Smith 350
  - A vocabulary of the Osage language, [communicated] Oct. 23, 1818; 23; 5p.; [Murray, Dr.]
    Communicated by John C. Warren from Murray, "who resides at Louisville."
    Freeman and Smith 2611
  - [Circular requesting that Indian languages of the U.S. be recorded and sent to the War Department], 24; 1p.; James Barbour
    Freeman and Smith 1973. Duplicate in Broadside Collection, no. 112.
  - Vocabulary of the extinct Haytian or Taino language, 25; 3p.; C[onstantine] S. Rafinesque
    Comparing Taino to Old World language (berber, Cantabrian, Celtic, Coptic, etc.
    Freeman and Smith 3708
  - Vocabulary of the Chontal language and its dialects s reading from Guatimala to Panama & Darien, Sept. 1826; 26; 7p.; C[onstantine] S. Rafinesque
    Includes some commentary on comparative linguistics of indigenous languages of Guatemala.
    Freeman and Smith 746
  - ALS to Robert Walsh, March 21, 1825; 27; 1p.; George Izard
    Offers services in collecting languages in Arkansas.
    Freeman and Smith 3095
  - ALS to George Izard, May 7, 1825; 28; 1p.; William H. Keating
    Freeman and Smith 3097
  - Report of committee to which George Izard's letter requesting data to guide his inquiries in Arkansas was referred, with notes for his guidance, May 6, 1825; 29, 30; 7p., 9p.; American Philosophical Society.
    Freeman and Smith 3092
  - ALS to the American Philosophical Society, Jan. 10, 1827; 31; 5p.; George Izard
    Transitting Quapaw vocabulary, with comments on mode of collection, and transmits specimens of a "water witch" and tarantulas.
    Freeman and Smith 3094
  - Report of committee to which was referred the communications of George Izard on the Arkansas territory and a vocabulary of the Quapaw language, [Jan. 18, 1828]; 32; 1p.; American Philosophical Society.
    Freeman and Smith 3093
  - Notes respecting the Arkansas territory's aboriginal inhabitants, the Quapaw Indians, [Jan. 10 1827]; 33; 7p.; [George Izard]
    Freeman and Smith 3096
  - Vocabulary of the Quapaw Indians, [Jan. 10, 1827]; 34; 6p.; [George Izard]
    Freeman and Smith 3099
  - ALS Cy to Thomas Wistar, April 26, 1819; 35; 3p.; [Walter Bromley]
    Comparing Micmac and Delaware from resident of Halifax.
    Freeman and Smith 2238
  - A few specimens of the verbs of the Micmac Indians, [April 26, 1819]; 36; 8p.; [Walter Bromley]
  - A vocabulary of the language of the Delawares of New Sweden, translated by Peter S. Du Ponceau, 37; 4p.; [John] Campanius Holm
  - A vocabulary of the language of the Massachusetts Indians... extracted from Eliot's grammar and from his translation of the Bible and New Testament, 38; 2p.; Peter S. DuPonceau
    Regarding efforts to learn Cherokee; recommending Daniel Butrick.
  - ALS to Peter S. Du Ponceau, July 20, 1818; 39; 3p.; John Gambold
    Complaining of white harassment of Cherokees to remove.
  - ALS to Peter S. Du Ponceau, Dec. 16, 1818; 40; 3p.; John Gambold
  - Conjugation of a verb in the Cherokee language, [Oct. 29, 1818]; 41; 4p.; Dan[iel] S. Butrick
  - Remarks on the verbs of the Cherokee language; Sounds of the Cherokee, 42; 2p.; Dan[iel] S. Butrick
  - ALS to Peter S. Du Ponceau, Aug. 8, 1818; 43; 3p.; Robert, Vicar general of Quebec
    Relaying information on contacts for Catholic missionaries among the Iroquois, Algonkian, Abnakis, and Micmac of Lower Canada.
  - Queries concerning the northern Indians, March 31, 1797; 44; 2p.; [Benjamin Smith Barton]
  - Answers to Dr. Benjamin Smith Bartton's queries concerning the northern Indians, for David Zeisberger, [ca.1797]; 45; 3p.; Gottlob Senseman
  - Answers to Dr. Benjamin Smith Barton's queries on the Northern Indians, 1797-1798; 46; 7p.; Heckewelder, John Gottlieb Ernestus, 1743-1823; Zeisberger, David, 1721-1808
  - ALS to William Short, May 25, 1784; 47; 1p.; R[ichard] Kells
    Has engaged Mr. Gurley, a clergyman, to collect vocabulary for Jefferson among the Nottoway.
  - ALS to Rich[ar]d Kells, May 15, 1784; 48; 1p.; Geo[rge] Gurley
  - Remarks on Indian names still to be found, [May 25, 1784]; 49; 2p.; [George Gurley]
    Etymology of "Tuckahoe" and other Nottoway rods, tracing them to Arabic and Hebrew roots.